同学们好，我是Yan
hey hello students I'm Yan
这是另一个PWN大学视频
and this is yet another pwn college video
具体来说是关于shellcoding的视频
specifically a video on shellcoding
这期PWN学院教学视频介绍了的shellcoding
this is an introduction of the shellcoding module of pwn college
希望你们有
hopefully you have
了解过计算机架构
come to this module knowing computer architecture
一些汇编基础知识
some assembly fundamentals and
二进制文件结构等等
what a binary file is and so forth
如果你缺失其中的一些知识
if you're missing some of this knowledge
我们有一系列的基础视频
we have a series of fundamental videos
我强烈建议你在尝试这个模块之前去看一下
that I highly recommend you go watch before trying this module
好了，首先复习一下计算机基础知识
all right let's get started as a review from those computer fundamentals
主要是计算机架构相关
specifically computer architecture fundamental video
现代计算机架构中
the modern computer architecture
最受欢迎的
that is most popular let's say among the
你每天都用的
systems that you will interact with consciously on the daily basis
是冯·诺伊曼架构
is the von noiman architecture
该架构以这三位之一命名，他们发明了这种架构
named after one of these 3 Johns that brought us this architecture
冯·诺伊曼架构
von noiman architecture
与其它的架构，比如哈佛的架构，
as opposed to some other architecture such as the Harvard architecture
在设计理念上不同
you know kind of philosophical design
它对数据和代码是没有明显区分的
treats data and code interchangeably
冯·诺伊曼架构基本上是这样的
the von noiman architecture is basically this
存储金字塔（硬盘、内存、多级cache、寄存器）
methuroshicum doller of caching layers
数据在这些缓存层之间流动
and data flows between these caching layers
从互联网到你的磁盘到你的内存再到你的
from the open internet to your disk to your memory to your
CPU缓存到CPU寄存器等等
CPU cache to CPU registers at so forth
这些数据可以是
and these data can be
这些数据可以是代码，也可以是数据
these data can be code or data interchangeally
这会导致一些问题
this can cause problems
我们深入研究一个可能导致的安全问题具体示例
so let's dive into one specific example of a security problem that this can cause
这是一个程序
here's a program that
一个我自己写的规模不大的程序
a not various scale program myself wrote
写的过程中
and in the course of writing
这个程序有几个bug
this program made several bugs
这节课我们将讨论一个特定的bug
we're going to talk about one specific bug in this lecture
在未来的模块中，我们将讨论其他bug
in future module we'll talk about other bugs
但这个特定的漏洞会让攻击者
but this specific bug allows an attacker
实现shellcode执行
to achieve shellcode execution
即注入会被执行的二进制代码到程序
that is to inject binary code that will be executed
并且和该程序有相同权限
under the exact permissions and so forth of this program
和这个程序有相同的上下文
right on in the context of this program
这是怎么发生的呢
so how does this happen
让我们来看看这个程序
well let's take a look at this program
首先看到这两个bye函数
1st thing that you see is 2 different functions that say bye
还有一个hello函数
one function that says hello
hello函数接受一个指向bye函数的指针
the hello function actually takes a pointer to the bye function
并调用它
and invokes it
函数指针是C和某些其他编程语言的一个特性
function pointers are a feature of C and certain other programming languages
允许你在运行时定位到并调用
that allow you at runtime to target
这些函数指针指向的代码段地址
the calling of these pointers to different places in memory
hello函数接收一个内存地址
right so this hello function receives a memory address
当到了该说再见的时候
and when it's time to say goodbye
它会调用这个内存地址
it invokes that memory address
这不是一个罕见的模式
this is not a rare pattern
它在复杂代码中使用得非常频繁
it's used actually quite frequently in complex code basis
会在程序中四处传递这些函数指针
right passing around these function pointers
再看看这个程序的主要功能
and you look at the main functionality of this program
可以看到首先会读取一个name变量
you see that at 1st reads a name
实际上这里还有另一个弱点我们之后会讲到（缓冲区溢出）
and here's actually where there is another vulnerability that's we'll deal with that later
这个程序读取一个name
this program reads a name
然后随机用2个bye函数之一调用hello
and then chooses randomly to invoke the hello function with one of the 2 good bye functions
bye1或bye2
right either bye1 or bye2
如果它使用了bye2，一切看起来都很好
and if it uses bye2 it all looks great
它传递一个name，那是你输入的名字
there's a name that it passes that's the name you input
然后是函数指针
and then there is the function pointer
但是当第一种情况发生时，当它使用bye1时
but when it uses the 1st case when it uses bye1
颠倒了传参顺序
it reverses the order
程序员犯了一个错误
the programmer myself made a mistake
在这个小程序中，这个错误是可笑的
and in this tiny program this mistake is laughable
但还是在一个大的代码库中
but in a large code base again
这是一个容易犯的错误
this is a very easy mistake to make
记错了参数顺序
just a mix up of argument order
bye1作为name传入
so bye1 gets passed in as the name
所以现在name收到了二进制代码地址
so the name is now binary code
现在代码被视作为数据
so the data is or the code is being treated as data
更糟糕的是输入的名字原本是数据
and what's worse is my name which is data
现在被视为代码
is now being treated as code
那么这意味着什么呢
so what are the implications of this
这意味着
all right the implication of this is
当要调用bye函数时
when the bye function gets involved
bye函数指针
the bye function pointer
当程序执行跳转到传递给hello函数的地址时
when the program execution jumps to the address that was passed into the hello function
程序执行被转移到栈中
program execution gets transferred into the stack
跳转到了name变量所在的位置
where my name that I inputted lives
这很糟糕
this is very bad
当然
of course
现代计算机有对应的保护机制
modern computers have mitigations against this
因为这是一个很常见的问题
because this is such a common issue
不一定是这种特定的漏洞，但总的来说是常见的问题
maybe not through this specific vulnerability pattern but in general
我们将在禁用保护机制(DEP)的情况下编译这个程序
we're going to compile this program with these with mitigations disable
execstack
this is what the execstack is
我将在后面的视频中它讨论如何使栈不再具有可执行权限
I'll talk in a later video about how the stack is nolonger executable
这样才不会发生这种事
so that this cannot happen
尽管（DEP）并没有使shellcode无用
although this does not make shellcode useless
我在后面的视频中也会讲到，但是
that I'll talk about in that video as well but
为了这次介绍的目的
for the purposes of this introduction
我们将用这个选项禁用这种保护机制
we're going to disable that mitigation with this option
让我们来看看它是如何工作的
so let's take a look out of how this works
好吧
all right
这是我们的程序，hello.c
here is our program hello.C
和幻灯片上的一样
exactly as on the slides
如果我们编译它
if we compile it
我们要取消所有的警告
we're gonna just disable all of the warnings
有一个警告是不能禁用的
there's one warning that you cannot disable in
那就是你永远永远永远不要在任何情况使用gets
that is that you should never ever ever ever use gets in anything
gets函数接收输入直到新行
the gets function it receives input until a new line
不管输入有多少
and doesn't care how much input
所以它会溢出你试图存储输入的任何变量
so it'll overflow any sort of variables that  that you try to contain the input in
好的，但是我们用它是因为它很简单
alright but we're using it because it's easy
我们运行hello函数
so we run the hello function
它要我输入我的名字，然后等待
it asks for my name just hangs
我输入了Yan，幸运的是
I hit Yan and luckily
恰巧是farewell输出
we hit the farewell case
如果你还记得
if you recall
farewell输出代表调用的bye2
the farewell case is bye2
这时调用传参没有问题
and bye2 is properly passed in
Bye1是传入错误位置的那个
bye1 is the one that's passed in in the wrong location
让我们继续试试
let's keep trying yon
再试一次，再试一次
hit it again try again
boom
程序崩溃
program crashes
这里你可以看到它打印了一些垃圾
so here you can see that it printed some garbage
最有可能的情况是它打印了hello
most likely what happened is it printed hello
然后遇到一个return字符(\r)
and then there was a character return
它把光标放回了行首
which puts the print back to the beginning of the line
然后继续输出了些东西（!号）
then the prints have more stuff right
最后输出非法指令
and then there was an illegal instruction
然后程序崩溃了
and the program crashed
好的，让我们用GDB更深入地看一下
alright let's take a look a little bit deeper in GDB
进入调试器
so here we are in a debugger
让我们运行启动程序
let's run starting program
输入Yan，运气好没崩
put in Yan got lucky
很幸运
got lucky
boom 崩了
boom okay here's our illegal instruction
你马上就能看到一些东西
immediately you can see a couple of things
如果你看一下进程内存映射
if you look at the process mapped memory
你们可以看到
so you can see that
hello映射在这个地址
hello is loaded at this address here
5...54000, 之后还有几页内存
there's 5 5 000 000 and you know a couple of pages after that
如果你不熟悉这个
if this isn't familiar to you
请回去看
please go back and watch the
pwn学院的计算机基础系列Linux二进制或Linux进程加载视频
Linux binary or Linux process loading video in the computer fundamentals of pwn college
这也在pwn.college这个模块上给出了链接
it'll be also LinkedIn from this module on pwn.college
你很容易就能找到那个视频
so you can easily find that video
我们在这里看到的
what we see here
我们离那个程序的位置很远
is that we are nowhere near that the location of that program
事实上，程序崩溃的时候处在栈上
in fact we are in the stack where we're crashing
如果你看一下
and if you see
rip的值或者说在哪里崩溃的
what is at the instruction point or where we're crashing
能看到我名字最后两个字母
we see that it is the last 2 letters of my name
所以我名字的第一个字母
so the 1st letter my name
是一条对应的有效指令
must have been a valid instruction
我们来看看这是什么
which it is let's take a look at what that is
我名字的第一个字母
the 1st letter my name is
在x86 64汇编语法中尝试弹出RCX
trying to  pop RCX in x86 64 assembly
很酷的东西
pretty cool stuff
我们注入了shellcode
okay so we have injected shellcode
我们将二进制代码直接注入到了应用程序中
we have injected binary code directly into the application in a way
应用程序会执行它
that application will execute it
这非常简单
this was super simple
它是由程序员混淆了2个参数的顺序引起的
it it was caused by a programmer mixing up the order of 2 arguments
想象一下，好吧
imagine that all right
这不仅仅是理论上的事情
this isn't just a theoretical thing
这在现实已经出现了20多年
this has been seen in the wild for over 20 years
事实上超过30年
in fact over 30 years
1988年罗伯特·塔潘·莫里斯
in 1988 Robert Tappan Morris a
我记得
I think
他刚从哈佛毕业，或者是和一个哈佛学生一起
he had either just graduated from Harvard or with a Harvard student at the time
创建了第一个文档版本
created the 1st documented version
计算机蠕虫的第一个有记载的例子
the 1st documented example of all computer worm
使用第一个记录的shellcode示例
using the 1st documented example of shellcode
也是第一个有记录的缓冲区溢出
and of actually a buffer overflowing
打破了很多第一次
a lot of you know 1st right
这些想法和概念当时已经流传了一段时间
these ideas and concepts have been floating around in the wild for a while
但
but
摩尔斯蠕虫是第一个在实践中展示证明它们的
the morse worm was the 1st to demonstrate them in practice
所以莫尔斯虫作为同类中的第一个，实际上是非常复杂的
so the morse worm was actually surprisingly complicated for the 1st worm of its kind
但它利用的其中之一是缓冲区溢出
but one of the vectors that it exploited was a buffer overflow
在fingerd服务中的栈缓冲区溢出
a stack buffer overflow in fingerd
实际上和这里的一个漏洞非常相似
actually something very similar very very similar to the vulnerability
和我们示例程序中的gets函数漏洞很相似
the other vulnerability that gets call in our example program
我们会在以后的课上讲到
but we'll talk about that in a future module
它使用这个注入shellcode来运行命令
it used this to inject shellcode to run commands
从受害机器中获得立足之地
to gain a foothold in the machine from the victim machine
然后控制受害机器扫描邻近的主机并感染它们来传播蠕虫
from which we just scanned adjacent host and infected them to propagate the worm
这件事让整个互联网瘫痪了
and this thing shut down the internet
为了让互联网恢复正常
in order to bring the internet back up
人们基本上切断了整个互联网
people disconnected essentially the whole internet
然后关闭各个网络来修复蠕虫病毒
and then shut there individual networks down to fix the worm
重新启动
bring them back up
然后重新连接到网络上
and then reconnect it to the reconnected the internet
好吧，想象一下如果现在有什么东西关闭了互联网
right imagine something shutting down the internet today
那将十分混乱
will be chaos
尤其是现在
you know especially nowadays
我录制视频这段时间COVID - 19大流行
as I'm recording this video during the COVID 19 pandemic
基本上什么都依赖互联网
where be relying internet for basically everything
有趣的是你可以试试
interestingly you can try
自己玩玩这个链接中的莫尔斯蠕虫
to mess with the morse worm yourself at this link down here
或者至少尝试利用莫尔斯蠕虫所利用的漏洞
or at least try to exploit the vulnerability that the morse worm took advantage of
这可能和其他几个模块相关
this might be more relevant a couple of modules away so
你可能不具备所需的背景知识
you might not have the background knowledge needed
但请先记住这一点
yet but keep that in mind
当我认为时间到了的时候，也会提醒你
also give it a shout out when I think it is time for you
试一试这种漏洞利用
to give that exploitation a try
好吧
all right
为什么叫它shellcode呢
so why do we call it shellcode
我们称之为shellcode
well we call it shellcode
因为这是典型的传统目标
because the typical kind of traditional goal of this exploit
是在机器上获得shell
is to gain get a shell on the machine
运行/bin/sh之类的程序
is to run something like bin sh
因此我们称之为shellcode
thus we call it shellcode
这是一个例子
so this is an example that
它调用了execve系统调用 使用了bin sh和2个空参数
cause this system call execve bin sh with 2 null arguments
如果你不熟悉系统调用这个词
if the word system calls unfamiliar to you
请回头看汇编语言基础的视频
please go back and watch the assembly language fundamentals video
或者Linux进程执行基础视频
or the Linux process execution fundamentals video
最好都看看
ideally both all right so
这将设置一个execve系统调用
this sets up an execve system call
59是execve的系统调用号
59 is the syscall number of execve
它把它放入RAX
so it puts that into RAX
rax是传入系统调用号的位置
that's where the syscall number goes
然后它加载第一个参数到RDI中
then it loads into the 1st argument a slot RDI
字符串bin sh 的地址
the address of the string bin sh
这是我们要执行的程序
that's what we'll be executed
它实际在这里
and we have this down here
rip + binsh 这种格式
this format rip plus binsh
这当然是指令指针加上到binsh的偏移量
so this is of course the instruction pointer plus the offset to binsh
这就是它的含义
that's what this stands for
LEA全称加载有效地址
LEA stands for load effective address
binsh的地址是一个相对于rip的偏移
and so the address of binsh as it is relative from rip
它被加载到RDI中
gets loaded into RDI
这很酷，因为
this is very cool because
这意味着这个shellcode
this means that this shellcode just
形成一个可以放在内存中任何位置的块
forms a block that you can put anywhere in memory
这将找到bin sh路径
and this will find the  bin sh path
然后我们参数2和3都传null
then we null out argument 2 and 3
这个方法是正确的
the way exactly works
这很好，它运行时没有命令行参数，没有环境变量
this is good this just runs it with no arguments and and no environment variables
如果你不熟悉这些术语
again if those terms are unfamiliar with you
请回去看
please go back and watch the
Linux进程执行基础视频
Linux process execution fundamentals video
然后触发系统调用
and then it triggers the syscall
这是AMD 64也称为x8664汇编的shellcode，
so this is shellcode in AMD 64 also known as x8664 assembly
这将得到一个shell
that gains a shell
让我们来看看它是如何工作的
let's take a look at how it works
让我们退出之前的GDB
let's get out of our GDB session from earlier
所以实际上我会
so actually I'll
请稍等，我等一下再讲它是如何工作的
bear with me I'll take a look at how it works in a 2nd
当我讲到如何编译shell代码时
when I talk about how to actually compile the shellcodes
所以我们要先讨论一下如何编译shellcode
so we have to talk about that 1st
好吧
all right
首先我要讲一下这个.string
1st thing I'll point out there's this dot string thing
好的，再次声明
right so again
冯·诺曼建筑的数据编码都是不区分的
von Norman architecture's data encode all mixed up
你可以把数据放在你的shellcode中
you can put data in your shellcode
这里，我们把这个字符串放在这里
in this case we put this string here
你也可以放任意字节
you can also put arbitrary bytes
实际上还有很多其他的
there's actually a lot of other
用于输入浮点数的指令
directives for putting in floating point numbers
等等等等等等
et cetera et cetera et cetera
你可能在编写shellcode的过程中
you likely in the course of writing shellcode
仅用.byte添加数据
only really interact with adding data with .byte
或使用.string添加数据
and adding data with .string
因此.string添加了一个字符串，并在它后面放了一个空字节
so .string adds a string and puts a null byte after it
如果您不熟悉以null结尾的字符串的概念
if the concept of nul terminated strings is not familiar to you please
回顾一下你的C语言知识
go back and review your C knowledge
这应该是你在学习C语言时学到的一个概念
that should be a concept that you learn when you learn C
当你输入.byte时，它会直接存储字节
when you put .byte it just dumps the bytes directly
这是在shellcode中嵌入数据的一种方式
this is one way of embedding data in your shellcode
好
right
这是我们在这个例子中使用的方法
and that's the way that we used in our example here
我们把这个字符串放在这里
we put this string right here
其他方式，我在这里讲一个
other ways I'll go through one here
你可以把它压倒栈上
so you can push it onto the stack
这里我们把数据加载RBX上
so here what we do is we move this data to RBX
然后我们把RBX压到栈上
and we push RBX onto the stack
然后我们把
and then we move
栈指针当前所指向的地址
the address where the stack pointer are currently points to
就是我们刚写入数据的位置
which is where our data was just written
加载到RDI
to RDI
在这个例子中，我们做了同样的事情
so in this case we did the same thing
抱歉，回到第一种情况
sorry back in the 1st case
这将binsh的地址加载到rdi中
this loaded the address of binsh into rdi
然而这个将bin sh压入栈
and then this pushes bin sh onto the stack
在栈上有/ bin / sh
so on the stack you have slash bin slash sh
你可以看到这些ASCII值
and you can see that this is the ASCII values
是反过来的字符
of the bytes of the characters backwards
因为这是个小端序系统
because this is a little endian system
我们把它压到栈中，然后
and we push it to the stack and then
我们取栈指针
we take the stack pointer
它指向我们刚才压入栈的字符串
which is pointing at that string we just pushed
然后把它加载到RDI
and remove that to RDI
所以这两种方式
so in both of these routes
RDI都指向堆栈（口误）
RDI is pointing to the stack
对不起，RDI都指向bin sh
there is sorry RDI is pointing to bin sh
有一个shellcode不是为获取shell而设计的
there is a shellcode that is not designed to get a shell
那并不总是你的目标
that's not always your goal
事实上，在这门课上，它是你的目标
in fact in this class it will work as your goal
但要求更低
but it's much easier to just
不好意思，读取flag就行
sorry it's much easier to just read the flag directly
尽管shell代码实际上有点复杂
although the shellcode is actually a little more complicated
这个shellcode
so this shellcode
是打开flag文件的shellcode
is a shellcode that opens the flag file
然后用一个叫send file的系统把文件发送过来
and uses a system called send file to send the file over
这个shellcode使用了
this shellcode uses the concepts of
Linux文件描述符，这是Linux跟踪文件的方式
Linux file descriptors which is how Linux tracks files
这是一个open系统调用
so here is the open syscall the
使用了压栈的方法传入/flag
use the pushing method to push the slash flag file name
所以我们把/flag加载到RBX
right so we move slash flag into RBX
我们压RBX入栈
we push RBX
然后我们将rsp加载到RDI
and then later on we move that rsp into RDI
这是open的第一个参数，然后
that's the 1st argument to open and then
open是2号系统调用
open is system call number 2
所以我们把2移到RAX中
so we move 2 into RAX
然后是RSI
and then into RSI
最后一个参数是null
this last argument we put a null
这实际上是只读打开文件的值
which is actually the value of signifying to open the file read only
我们会做一个系统调用
and we're gonna do a syscall
这个会打开 /flag文件
so this open slash flag
然后我们设置sendfile参数
and then we set up the sendfile arguments and so
您可以调出手册页查看sendfile
sendfile and you can pull up the man page
我展示一下
and I will show you that you can pull up the man page
这里，sendfile在2个文件描述符之间传输数据
here sendfile transfer data between 2 file descriptors
参数是输出文件的描述符
and arguments are the output file descriptor
输入文件描述符
the input file descriptor
以字节为单位的文件偏移量
the offset into the file in bytes
我们只想从头读
we just want to read from the beginning
以及要读取的字节数
and the number of bytes to read and go to read a bunch
调用的方法是
right and the way that we set it up
先设置第一个参数为1
is we set up the 1st argument 1
这是Linux的标准输出
so that's standard output in Linux
它会把结果打印到屏幕上
so that you know it just prints it out to the screen
第二个参数是第一个系统调用的返回值
the 2nd argument is the return from the 1st syscall
被打开文件的文件描述符
the file descriptor of the open file
这个可能是3
this will likely be 3
但不一定是。可能是
but doesn't have to be. there could be some random stuff
一个随机数
a random number
这取决于之前打开过多少文件
depending on how many files have previously been opened
我们从头读，读1000字节
and we read from the beginning and we read 1000
我们把这些都准备好了
and we set all that up
sendfile的系统调用号是40
the syscall number for sendfile is 40
然后我们调用系统调用
and then we call syscall
现在我们调用了
and so now we do
open sendfile
然后这里我们调用了系统调用exit
and then here we have a system call exit
这样shellcode就干净地退出了
so that the shellcode exits cleanly
我们在之前的execve shellcode中没有这样做
we didn't do that in our previous execve shellcode
因为在Linux加载基础知识视频中讨论过
because execve as discussed in the Linux loading fundamentals video
execve实际上是将整个进程替换为一个新的进程
actually replaces the whole process with a new process
因此，用bin sh完全替换了您正在利用的进程
so to replace your process that you're exploiting with bin sh completely
这个shellcode没有
this shellcode does not
为了避免崩溃
so in order to avoid crashes
因为这让人很难理解
which make it very hard to understand
你的shellcode崩溃了吗
did your shellcode crash
或者在shellcode执行后程序崩溃了
or did the program crash after your shellcode executed
所以我们直接退出程序
we cleanly exit the program
很好
cool all right
现在我们终于开始构建我们的shellcode了
now finally we have moved on to building our shellcode
所以我们把shellcode写成汇编代码
so we write our shellcode as assembly code
代码有一些固定步骤
there's some boilerplate that we need
建立一个全局符号
to set up a global symbol
它是shellcode的开始
that is the start of the shellcode
当我们把它汇编成二进制文件时
that when we assemble it into a binary file
我们可以像普通文件一样执行它
we can actually just execute it like a normal file
这有助于调试
this really helps debugging
这里是开始标签的位置
let me say okay here's where the start label is
顺便说一下，我们使用的是intel风格语法
and then we say by the way we're using Intel syntax
默认情况下，这些工具将使用AT&T风格语法
by default the tools will be using use at&t syntax
这个语法风格很烦人
it's very annoying
两种语法不兼容，但是
it is the wrong syntax but
幸运的是，我们可以使用一个选项来使用Intel风格语法
be luckily we can use an option to use Intel syntax
这里我们设置好了我们之前看过的shellcode
and here we are setting up our binsh shellcode that we looked at earlier
然后我们把它汇编起来
then we assemble it
把它汇编成一个ELF文件，一个可以执行的程序
we'll assemble it into a an ELF file into a program that we can run
我们不将标准库汇编到程序种
we assemble it without the standard libraries
因为我们不需要他们
because we don't need them
我们不用它们
we don't use them
我们使用系统调用直接调用内核
we directly call using system calls into the kernel
我们创建一个静态链接的程序
and we create a static file
也因为这更容易演示
also because this makes it easier in certain situations
动态加载器不会参与它的执行
it doesn't invoke the dynamic loader at all
什么都没有
nothing is  just
只有你的shellcode在自己运行
here is your shellcode running directly in the self
这很令人兴奋
that's pretty exciting
这是
this is
顺便说一下，这产生的是一个程序而不是shellcode
by the way this produces a program not shellcode
它生成一个实际的程序，带有elf头等等
it produces an actual program with an elf header etc etc
这你应该知道
as you should know
如果你不知道
and if you don't
请回顾一下关于什么是二进制文件的基础课程
please go back and watch the fundamentals lecture on what is a binary file
ELF文件包含一个.text节
your ELF file contains a .text section
.text节里存放的shellcode
with the shellcode
准确的说是装着你程序的代码
with the code of your program
但在这个情况下
in this case
整个程序代码就是shellcode
the whole code of your program is the shellcode
你可以使用objcopy
and you can use objcopy
将shellcode复制出来
to copy that shellcode out
得到的shellcode-raw是shellcode的字节码
and now that resulting shellcode dash raw file are the bytes of your shellcode
你会将它注入到利用程序中
that you would have inject in your exploit
这很令人兴奋
that's pretty exciting
我们来看看具体怎么做
so let's let's take a look at how this would work
好
alright
这是我们的shellcode
here is our shellcode shellcode s
和幻灯片上的shellcode是一样的
it's the same shellcode that's on the slides
只是调用了execve binsh
just calls execve binsh
如果我们编译它
if we compile it
使用-nostdlib
-nostdlib
我们不需要标准库
we don't need the standard library
静态链接，只是为了简单起见
static just to simplify some things
shellcode.s -o shellcode-elf
编译好了，当你运行shellcode-elf
it compiles and when you run shellcode elf
boom
它执行了binsh，我们获得了一个shell
it runs the binsh and we have a shell
当然了我们之前就有一个shell
of course we had a shell before
但
but
没有人抱怨
no one is complaining
我们先反汇编一下看看
let's disassemble it real quick
看看我们需要的shellcode
just to see that it has our shellcode
当然用intel格式看
and Intel format of course
这里很简洁
and here it is nice and simple
在程序开始时
in the start of the program
这是mov rax59
here we have our mov rax 59
十六进制是0x3b
that is ox 3b in hexdecimal
加载rip+0x10地址
load the address of rip+0x10
这是bin SH
that's our bin SH
我们把0加载到RSI和RDX
we move 0 to  RSI and RDX
它们是argv和环境变量
that is the RGV and the environment
然后触发系统调用
then we trigger the syscall
很好，复制出来
cool so let's copy out
这将把text节拷贝到
this will dump the text section into
到我们的shellcode原始文件
into our shellcode raw file
好，现在我们可以用hexdump查看shellcode-raw
all right and now we can hex dump shellcode-raw
你可以看到它们是相同的字节
and you can see it's the same bytes
48 c7 c0，一直到末尾的bin sh
48 c 7 c0 and so on all the way to the end of bin sh
我应该指出一件事
I should point out one thing
当我们反汇编我们的shellcode的时候
when we were disassembling our shellcode
objdump认不出binsh是字符串，它也会把它当作指令反汇编
of course not knowing any better objdump tried to disassemble binsh as well
知道就好了
but you know you'll have to deal with that on your own all right
这就是objectum的工作方式。这就是我们的shellcode
I mean it's just how objectum happens to work but here's our shellcode
这个shellcode我们现在可以
this is the shellcode that we can now
直接注入到我们的漏洞程序中
transferred directly into our vulnerable program
我们可以把这个shellcode cat输出到hello中
so we can cat out this shellcode into our hello
作为提醒，hello，输入我的名字
as a reminder hello put in my name
后会直接执行一个shellcode（1/2的概率）
and that gets excuted directly a shellcode um
这里本来没准备讲
this is going off script a little bit
我本来没想要执行这个
I didn't actually think to run this
而我现在所做的是
and what I'm doing right here is
首先打印出shellcode
1st printing out the the shellcode
然后放到一个交互环境
and then just dropping in to an interactive
就像cat，可以接收输入并能打印输出
like a cat that raise my input and rise the output
否则，如果我直接cat输出shellcode
otherwise I'll cat out the shellcode
到运行的hello，它会启动一个bin sh
run hello it'll run bin sh
然后bin sh将立即终止
and then bin sh will terminate immediately
因为不会有后续输入
because there's no further input
因为shellcode代码已经执行完了
because the shellcode code is done
好了，开始吧
alright here we go
oops打错了，cat shellcode-raw
oops cat shellcode raw
我们得到了一个shell。我按了回车键
and we have a shell I to hit enter
因为gets会一直读取，直到遇到新的行
because gets will keep reading until a new line appears
然而我没有加一条新行
and I didn't put a new line in
我们加一个新行进去
let's actually put a new line in
这将会echo一个新的行
so this will echo a new line
这将追加到shellcode原始文件
and this will appended to the shellcode raw file
我们用hexdump看一下shellcode-raw
now let's hex dump shellcode raw
这回有了一个新行
there's now a new line here
这很酷
that's very cool
然后我们再运行一次
then we run it again
所以
so
看，它走了farewell的分支
see it did farewell
所以不是我们要的情况
so it didn't hit the right case
现在是我们要的情况
there now it hit the right case
现在我们黑进去了
and now we are in
现在在我的机器上通过漏洞利用注入shellcode获得了yans用户shell
we have a shell on my machine through an exploit by injecting shellcode as my user
很酷啊
pretty cool huh
按下退出，程序就退出了
can hit exit and now that program's dead
这就是shellcode的工作原理
all right so that is how shellcode works
我们现在已经构建了shellcode，接下来做什么
we've now built shellcode what's next
我们已经知道如何运行它了
we already saw how to run it
我刚刚演示过了
actually I jumped ahead a little bit
但我要重申一下
but just to reiterate
这样编译的好处
the nice thing about compiling it in this
用我教的这个方法汇编shellcode的好处是
assembling your shellcode in this method that I've taught you
你可以直接运行它
is that you can run it directly
调试它等等
and also debug it and so forth
我们很快就会讲到这些
as we will get to very shortly
有趣的是
interesting thing here
有很多不同的方法来编写shellcode和
there are a lot of different methods to write shellcode and
汇编shellcode
and specifically to assemble shellcode
还有其他的汇编程序
there are other assemblers
不光可以使用GCC内置的工具
instead of using tooling built into GCC
还可以用其他汇编程序，如NASM和其他各种汇编程序
there are other assemblers such as NASM and various others
你可以使用这些
you can use those
但根据我的经验
but in my experience
这让事情变得更难了
it makes things a little bit harder
在这个课程中解决这些困难也不会让你受益
for reasons that you won't benefit from for this course
我建议使用我教的方法
I'd recommend using the method I taught
因为该方法非常容易调试
because that method is very easy to debug
而且对于amd64外的架构也非常适用，嗯超级适用
very applicable and actually is super applicable to other architectures than AMD 64
而其他汇编程序往往是特定于一种架构的
as well whereas other assemblers tend to be specific for one architecture
好
all right
如果你对编译为elf文件的shellcode运行器不满意
if you're not happy with the shellcode runner that gets compiled as your elf file
它就是一个elf文件封装的shellcode
which is just basically an elf wrapped around your shellcode
你可以创建一个C程序来加载你的shellcode
you can create a C program that load your shellcode
将它映射为可执行内存，然后执行它
map it as executable into memory and execute it
当您需要模拟非常棘手的条件时，这可能很有用
this might be useful when you need to simulate really tricky conditions
比如打开不同的文件之类的
open up different files stuff like that
你不想把这些都写在汇编中作为shellcode的序言
and you don't want to write that all in assembly as a preamble to your shellcode
那么这就是通常的做法
and this is generally how you would do it
你会创建一个指针函数叫做page
right you would create a pointer function pointer called page
申请一块可执行内存用来放代码
memory map a bunch of code that's executable
读入你的shellcode，并执行它
read your shellcode into it and execute it
然后注入它到测试程序，用和我们注入shellcode一样的方法
then you inject that in the same way  that we injected our shellcode into that tester program
那么如何调试shellcode呢
all right how do you debug shellcode
假设shellcode出错了
let's say shellcode is going wrong
要被这个问题逼疯了
something is driving you insane
很不顺利
and things aren't working well
一种高层次的方法是使用strace
one way from a high level is to use strace
对strace
right strace
从基本原理上你应该知道
as you should know from the fundamental
Strace是一个系统调用追踪器
strace is a system called tracer
它只是简单地在调试器里运行你的程序
it'll simply run your program with debugging
然后打印出所有你的程序调用的系统调用
and print out all of your all of the syscalls that your program does
让我们来看看
so let's take a look
首先，我们破坏shellcode
actually 1st let's break our shellcode
不如用binsh+1代替binsh
how about instead of binsh let's actually have it go binsh plus one
我不知道这能不能行
I have no idea of this will work
但
but
让
let
让我们编译一下
let's compile it
好的，可以了
okay it works alright
嗯
um
确切地说，是汇编的
or rather it come it is assembled
运行shellcode-elf  提示了非法指令
so shellcode-elf run it illegal instruction
哦，是个坏消息
oh that's bad news
我们的shellcode出了什么问题
what went wrong with our shellcode
啊，我们Strace它
ah we Strace it
这很酷很方便，得益于shellcode被放在elf文件中，很容易运行
this is an awesome result of the shellcode being inside a elf file and easily runnable
如果用strace查看它
if srace it
我们马上看到哪里出错了，它执行了bin/sh
we see right away what's wrong it executed bin sh
而不是/bin/sh
instead of slash bin slash sh
结果得到了一个没有这样的父目录
and got a no such father directory as a result
很好，然后我们修改它
cool then we modify it
修复它
fix it
重新汇编它
reassemble it
重新运行它
rerun it
然后我们看到它实际上在执行bin sh
and then we see that it is actually now executing bin sh
往上滑，它就在这里
and if you scroll up it's right here
非常酷
very cool all right
这就是用strace在高层次上调试shellcode的方法
so that is strace that's how you debug your shellcode on a high level
这能捕捉到shellcode中大量的错误
and this catches a shocking amount of errors that you make shellcoding
如果还不能解决
if you need something more
你可以用GDB调试shellcode
you can debug shellcode with GDB
因为它只是我们汇编出的一个普通Linux程序
it's just a Linux program the way that we assemble it
好的，让我们快速看一下
right so let's take a quick look
这张幻灯片可以作为很好的参考
and then this slide can be a good reference for you
如果我们在shellcode里犯了些傻错
if we again do something silly to our shellcode
如果我们
if we
我们可能犯什么错？
I don't know what what what might we do
可能不小心用了一些解引用
we might accidentally have some dereference here
这样是不好的
that's not good right so maybe
好的，我们加载大小指向的内存到RDX中
okay we're loading into RDX memory that our size pointing to
但是我们的大小指向0，所以它会崩溃
but our size pointing to  0 so it's gonna crash all right
但是它能汇编成功
but this will assemble
当我们运行它时，当然会报段错误
and when we run it it's seg faults of course
在GDB运行它
running in GDB run it
哦
oops
Shellcode-elf
shellcode dash elf
运行它
run it
这是segg错误
okay it's seg faulted
我们马上就能看到它在哪里出现了段错误
immediately we can see where did it seg fault
它在这里报的段错误
it's seg faulted at this
加载 rsi指向的内存 到 rdx
move into RDX the pointer to RSI
我们现在可以看到RSI的值
we can see what is RSI right now
或者说它指向什么
or what is it pointing to
你可以看到它是0，所以不能解引用
and you see that it is 0 and so can't be dereference
现在我们知道问题出在哪里了
now we know what's wrong
让我们快速看一下其他一些命令
let's take a quick look at some other commands that
我们可以在GDB中做一些其他有用的事情
some other useful things we can do in GDB
记住断点，因为示例没怎么用标签
keep in mind break points because there are no labels or
实际上，如果你在汇编代码中添加了标签，gdb里也会有标签
actually there can be labeled if you put in the labels
举个例子，你可以在GDB中
so you can actually set for example in GDB
尽管这（示例）毫无意义
although this makes no sense
在binsh处设置断点，gdb会设置好断点
break binsh and it sets it
可以（中断在断点处）。如果能运行到这个位置
and you can actually if if that was ever run
但实际上在这里你可以看到
but actually here you can see
添加更多的标签，这些标签没有实际意义
add more labels right these labels mean nothing really
好，标签1
say okay label one
标签2
label 2
然后我们汇编它
and then when we assemble it
GDB它，然后我们可以设置label1断点
GDB and we can do break label 1
设置label2断点
break label 2
运行并到达标签1 断点
run and we hit the break point label 1
这对于你的（调试）shellcode来说是一个很棒的功能
this is awesome functionality to be able to do for your shellcode
它也不会改变你的shellcode
and it doesn't actually modify your shellcode at all
加上这些标签后，你仍然可以提取你的shellcode
to have these labels you can still extract your shellcode
标签都在elf的其他部分
the labels are all in other parts of the elf
它只是让调试变得更加容易
it just makes debugging much much easier
我们还可以做其他事情
other things that we can do
如果你不想用这些标签
if you don't want to use those labels
记住
just keep in mind
要在你想要设置断点的地址前，放一个星号
before the address where you want to break you have to put a star
原因之一是程序是静态编译的
and one of the reasons that we compiled things statically
我稍后再讲另一个原因
I'll talk about another reason later
回忆一下我们创建了一个静态链接的elf执行文件
if you recall this creates a static elf
我们在二进制文件基础中讨论过静态链接的和动态链接的elf
again we talk about static and dynamic elfs in the binary files fundamentals
当你有一个静态链接的ELF时
but one of the reasons is when you have a static ELF
它总是映射或者说
it always maps or
它被编译成默认情况总是映射
it gets compiled in a way by default that it maps
所有东西到固定地址
everything into this fixed for all
而不是随机地址
instead of random memory
这样调试起来更容易一些
so it's a little easier to debug
好
alright
如果你想在某个内存地址中断
if you want to break at a memory location
记得在前面打个星号就行了
just remember put a star in front of it
有几件事运行起来有点奇怪
a couple of things that work kind of weirdly
在平常的开发中
in source code you're used to hitting
当你用GDB
when you're in GDB
调试一个你用-g编译的有调试符号的程序时
debugging a C program that you built with dash G for debug symbols
您可能习惯于按 s 来 步入一行代码
you're probably used to hitting s to step one line of code
这不是源代码，这是汇编代码
this is ain't source code this is assembly code
si 表示 步入执行一个指令
si  will step one instruction
不要用s，用si
don't use s use s I
si会跟进call指令（步入）
si will follow call instructions
有时候这就是你想要的
sometimes this what you want
有时你想call执行后
sometimes you want  call to execute and
再获得控制
then you want to get control again
这应该用ni
that is ni
下一个指令
next instruction
ni将跳过call（步过）
so next instruction will step over a call
call会先执行完，然后才会得到GDB shell
of course the call will execute and then you'll get your the GDB shell back
Si会步入这个调用
si will step into the call
两者都很有用
both are useful
但知道其中的区别很重要
but it's important to know the difference
使用这些修饰符会用不同的方法查看数据
there are different ways that you can look at data with these modifiers
这代表检查RSP指向的数据
this means examine the data that are RSP points to
并把它视为一个4字（64位）
and treated as one gigantic word
就是8字节，以十六进制展示
and this is 8 bytes in hexadecimal format
除了十六进制格式，还有其他选项包括
other options for the hexa decimal format includes
字符串，我在最开始演示hello程序的时候用过
string you saw me use that at the beginning when we were looking at hello the program
I表示整数
I for integer
不，不好意思，i表示指令，我记得d 表示
no sorry I for instruction and I think d for for for
十进制整数，x表示十六进制
decimal integer and X for hex
然后你当然可以
and then you can of course
直接用p来打印它们的值
use P to just print out their value
不使用这个表达式，不解引用这个寄存器
without the value of this expression or this register without dereferencing them
g表示8B， d表示4B， h表示2B和b表示1B
and we have G 1B d 4B H 2B and B 1B
你可以打印多个（2d表示2个4B）
and then you can print multiple
所以这些都表示打印8B
so all of these invocations will print 8B of whatever you're looking at
运行，继续，所有这些东西都正常工作
run and continue and all of this stuff works as normal
这只是一个Linux程序
this just a Linux program
恰好只包含了你的shellcode
just happens to only contain your shellcode
事实上，有用的反向执行
and in fact a useful thing is that reverse execution
你可以按这个链接设置反向执行
and you can go follow this link and set up reverse execution
也可以正常工作
also works as normal
所以你可以都试一下
so you can check all of that out
好了，最后一件关于调试shellcode的事
alright final thing we'll talk about in terms of debugging your shellcode
是硬编码断点
is hard coding in break points
事实证明，当在GDB中创建断点
it turns out that when you create a break point in GDB
我想说的是
I mean
断点有几种不同的类型
there are several different styles of break points
当您在GDB中创建一个普通的默认软件断点时
when you create a normal default software break point in GDB
它实际上会替换指令
it'll actually replace the instruction
在要添加断点的位置放上int 3指令
where you have a break point with an INT 3 instruction
Int 3指令是一条解码为cc的指令
int 3 instruction is a single instruction that decodes into cc
实际上你可以
you can actually
编码，抱歉，汇编成字节cc
or that encode sorry assembles into the byte cc
你可以看这里，我现在要试一下
you can look at it right here where I will now try it out
shellcode.s
让我们把这个bug和这些标签去掉
so let's take away this buggy thing and take away these labels
我们在这里放一个INT 3
instead we'll put an INT 3 here
这将在系统调用运行前注入一个硬代码断点到我们的shellcode中
so this will inject a hardcode break point into our shellcode right before syscall gets run
我们把它汇编起来
let's assemble it
如果你现在运行它，它会崩溃
great if you run it now it's gonna crash
因为我们没有附加调试器
because we don't have a debugger attached
我们也没有捕捉这个信号
and we're not capturing this sig trap
如果你用GDB运行它
if you run it with GDB
boom
我们正好在预期的位置进入断点
we get into a break point at exactly where we expected to
就在系统调用之前
right before that syscall
很酷，这很有用
very cool so this is a useful
当然在GDB中，通常你可以
I mean of course in GDB normally you can just say okay
在标签处中断或在地址处中断
break at the label or break at address
但是当你调试你正在利用的漏洞程序时
but when you are actually debugging the vulnerable program that you're exploiting
想在系统调用时中断
and you want to break at the syscall
这就简单多了
this is much easier
因为不总是知道你的shell最终会在哪里被调用等原因
it's much harder because you don't always know where your shell could will end up and so forth
所以在GDB调试器中设置断点要困难的多
to put in to set the debugger the break points in GDB
如果你在shellcode的开头放一个断点
so if you put a break point at the beginning of your shellcode
汇编
assemble
然后我们看一下
and then let's look at
你知道我们以前的版本
you know our old version of this
哇，真的
wow there really
什么鬼
what the hack
这就像连续抛5次硬币（每次都是一个结果）
this is like flipping like 5 in a row
好的，所以我们
all right and so we we
不再
of course we no longer
哦
oh
我们没用objcopy更新shellcode
we didn't objcopied out
现在我们有了带有调试器的版本
okay so now we have the version with the debugger
发生了什么
what's going on
你真的在执行吗
are you really hitting it
哦，我忘了按回车键
oh I forgot to hit enter
不好意思
sorry about this
我们现在已经覆盖了我们为get放入的新行
of course we've now overwrote that new line that we had put in there for the gets
现在好了，嘣
the gets okay now boom
好吧
okay
好了，执行了hello
there we go we hit hello
我们执行到了断点
and we hit that break point trap
现在如果在GDB中运行hello
now if you were running hello in GDB
它会进入调试器交互界面
it would have dropped us into a debugger
就像你之前看到的
just like you saw earlier
然后我们就可以调试shellcode了
and we can now debug the shellcode
不是必须要把它放在开头
and you don't have to put it in the beginning
这个int 3你可以把它放在任何你想要的地方
this int 3 you can put it anywhere you want
很酷的
cool
好的，接下来是什么
alright what is next
如何为其他架构编写shell代码
how do you write shellcode for other architectures
到目前为止，我们一直在谈论x86_64 AMD64
right so so far we've been talking about x8664 AMD64
用这个方法汇编获得shellcode
well it turns out with this method of assembling shellcode
用GCC中的工具，具体是GAS汇编器
using GCC essentially in this tool specifically gas assembler
方法几乎是一样的
turns out that it's almost the same
你可以在你的系统中安装一个交叉编译器
you can install a cross compiler in your system
你可以使用交叉编译器
and you can use that cross compiler
来编译MIPS的shellcode
to compile shellcode for MIPS
为MIPS组装外壳代码，这非常令人兴奋
assemble shellcode for MIPS which is super exciting
你也可以用模拟器运行那个shellcode
and you can also run that shellcode with an emulator
并在将其部署到实际系统之前进行测试
and test it out before deploying it on some real system
如果您使用qemu作为模拟器
if you use qemu as your emulator
Qemu有一个-strace选项
qemu has a dash strace option
如果你用strace查看qemu
if you strace qemu itself
qemu调用了很多系统调用
there's a lot of syscalls that qemu is calling
但如果你执行qemu -strace
but if you do qemu dash strace
Qemu会打印出所有
qemu itself will print out all the system calls
shellcode或者你模拟的程序调用的系统调用
that the shellcode or whatever program you're emulating is calling
如果你给它-g选项
and if you pass it the G option
它会为你的shellcode打开一个远程调试端口，这也非常棒
it'll open up a port for remote debugging for your shellcode which is pretty awesome too
这组工具对编写shellcode非常有用
so this set of tooling is really nice for shellcode
好吧
all right
如果你想要，需要练习的话
let's say you want to practice right which you do of course
这就是PWN大学的意义所在
that's what pwn college is all about
熟能生巧
practice makes perfect
去PWN学院
head over to pwn college
选择一个级别的shellcode作业
choose a level of the shellcoding homework
分析代码
analyze that code
理解你的shellcode必须满足的条件
and understand the constraints that your shellcode um must satisfy
以及修改你的shellcode
and the changes that will be made to your shellcode
并编写shellcode绕过它们
and write shellcode to bypass them
取决于你是哪一年看这个视频的
um depending on when in the year you're watching this video
作业服务可能会停半个星期
the challenges might be down for about half a week
我们要为下一届（这一届如果有的话）做准备
as we um prepare them for the next for this current class if there is one
那样的话，你就稍等一下
in that case just hold tight
挑战开始的时候我会宣布的
I'll announce when the challenges are available
然后你就可以去解决了。祝你好运
and then you can go solve them good luck